Guide to the Jon P. Gunnemann Files on Ethical Investments at Yale
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jon P. Gunnemann files on ethical investments at Yale
1952-1974
1969-1971
RU 1099
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.75
(6 boxes)
The files of ethicist Jon P. Gunnemann document a variety of activities on the topic of ethical investing in which he was involved while a graduate student at Yale University. The materials include correspondence, notes, background research files, and reports relating to the work of the Yale Student-Faculty Committee on Responsible Institutional Investment and the seminar on Yale's investments that grew out of the committee's work. The remainder of the collection consists of drafts and notes relating to the book The Ethical Investor: Universities and Corporate Responsibility, written by John G. Simon, Charles W. Powers, and Jon P. Gunnemann as a result of their work in the seminar.
Gunnemann, Jon P.
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 49 (YRG 49), Papers and projects on Yale.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jon P. Gunnemann, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Jon P. Gunnemann, a distinguished ethicist, retired in 2008 from Emory University, where he was a faculty member since 1981. He earned an A.B. from Harvard University in 1962, and an M.A. (1969) and Ph.D. (1975) from Yale University. In addition to his position at Emory, he also taught at the Pennsylvania State University from 1970-1976 and at Yale Divinity School from 1976-1981. Dr. Gunnemann's teaching and research have focused on ethics, economics, and politics, and he authored The Moral Meaning of Revolution, co-authored The Ethical Investor, and edited The Nation-State and Transnational Corporations in Conflict, along with many other articles and reviews.
Scope and Contents
The files of ethicist Jon P. Gunnemann document a variety of activities on the topic of ethical investing in which he was involved while a graduate student at Yale University. The materials include correspondence, notes, background research files, and reports relating to the work of the Yale Student-Faculty Committee on Responsible Institutional Investment and the seminar on Yale's investments that grew out of the committee's work. The remainder of the collection consists of drafts and notes relating to the book The Ethical Investor: Universities and Corporate Responsibility, written by John G. Simon, Charles W. Powers, and Jon P. Gunnemann as a result of their work in the seminar.
Beginning in 1968, Gunnemann was a key organizer of the Yale Student-Faculty Committee on Responsible Institutional Investment, which comprised undergraduate and graduate students and several members of the faculty interested primarily in the issue of investments in apartheid-era South Africa. The committee had the support of Yale's President, Kingman Brewster, Jr., and developed guidelines for a socially responsible investment program for Yale. In addition, the committee conceptualized a research seminar on Yale's investments, and sought and received grant funding from the Ford Foundation to offer this course during the 1969-1970 academic year. The seminar was an interdepartmental investigation into the economic, legal, and ethical challenges presented by universities accounting for moral and social issues in the management of their investment porfolios. Gunnemann served as the coordinator of the seminar, which was led by Professors John Simon, Yale Law School, and Charles Powers, Yale Divinity School.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by activity, there under alphabetically by topic.
Investments -- Moral and ethical aspects; Investments; Universities and colleges -- Finance; Gunnemann, Jon P.; Yale University -- Finance
- Jon P. Gunnemann Files on Ethical Investments at Yale, 1952-1974; Accession 2009-A-177
  - The Ethical Investor: Universities and Corporate Responsibility / by John G. Simon, Charles W. Powers, and Jon P. Gunnemann
    - Annotated drafts and notes, circa 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1-20)
    - Oversize materials, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Articles by book authors, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Gunnemann bibliographic note cards, Circa 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Simon, John, notes on issues that structured the book, Circa 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Social Responsibility and University Investments: An Essay Growing Out of a Seminar at Yale University / by John G. Simon, Charles W. Powers, and Jon P. Gunnemann, draft, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Yale investment seminar and project
    - Background files
      Scope and Contents
      Chiefly articles and brochures about the investment policies of academic institutions, corporations, and organizations.
      Arrangement
      Files are arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization, or in some cases, the author.
      - American Law Reports, "Duty of Trustees to Diversity Investments", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Antioch College, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Background articles and publications, 1952-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7-15)
        - Oversize materials, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
      - Brandeis, Dartmouth, and Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Brewster, Kingman, Jr., Carleton College commencement address and statement at Yale College faculty meeting, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Campaign GM (General Motors), Project on Corporate Responsibility, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Carter Berlind Weill, Circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Chase Manhattan, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Christman (Jesse), Detroit Episcopal, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Cornell University, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Council on Investment Priorities, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Fleming, Harold C., "Report on a Visit to South Africa", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Ford Foundation, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Harvard University, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - IRRC (Investment Responsiblity Research Center), 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Kalven report, University of Chicago, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - NACBS (National Affiliation of Concerned Business Students), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - National Catholic Conference for Interracial Justice, Project Equality, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - National Committee on Tithing in Investment, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - National Council of Churches, Corporate Responsibility and Religious Institutions, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Newspaper articles (black notebook), 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
        Black three-ringed binder removed for preservation purposes.
      - Princeton University, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Student Community Housing Corporation (New Haven), Circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Unitarian Universalist Association, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - United Church of Christ, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - YMCA (Young Men's Christian Association), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Bibliographic material, Circa 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Course materials, organizational, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - The Crow, volume II, numbers 8-13, 1969 June 7-August 25 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Newspaper of the Greater New Haven, Connecticut, Black community.
    - Decision Team, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Economics Team, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Endowment Management and Research Corporation, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Financial ledger, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Ford Foundation grant materials, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - GM (General Motors) issue, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Institutional problems, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Investment readings notes, Jon Gunnemann, Circa 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Legal Team, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - New Haven Team, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Notes, miscellaneous, Circa 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Pollution Team, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Powers (Charles), "Neutrality and Decision Models", Circal 1969-1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Requests for Yale Report, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Simon, John, "An Incomplete Discussion Outline of the 'Neutrality' Question", 1970 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - South African Team, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Student research teams, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Reports prepared by research team participants
        - Bookwalter, W.D., 1969 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        - Burt, Jeffrey, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        - Carens, Joseph, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
        - Cass, Richard, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
        - Collier, David, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
        - Doernberg, Richard, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
        - Ecklund, John, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
        - Egger, Mike, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
        - Giancola, Gerard, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
        - Hellén, Olof, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
        - Kahn, Marc, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
        - Lundgren, Dwight, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 13)
        - Neuwelt, Klari, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
        - Parker, P., 1970 (Box 4, Folder 15)
        - Potter, Barr, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 16)
        - Spitzer, Hugh, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
        - Stallkamp, DePaul, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 18)
        - Tobin, James, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Syllabus and related materials, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Yale governance study, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Yale Student-Faculty Committee on Responsible Institutional Investment
    - Correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Gunnemann report and related materials, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Meeting materials, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Notes from meetings, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 24)